Register of the Milton Friedman papers 77011.4088897
Hoover Institution Archives
- Incremental Speeches and Writings, 1935-2006 (Boxes 216-234)
  - Book reviews, A-Z (Box-folder 218: 1-11)
  - Permission to translate
    - A-Z, 1961-2006 (Box-folder 219: 1-7)
    - A-Z, 1964-1983 (Box-folder 219: 8-10)
  - Aldine Publishing Company, 1963-1976 (Box-folder 220: 1)
  - Cambridge Economic Handbook, 1955-1962 (Box-folder 220: 2)
  - Capitalism and Freedom, 1964-2006 (Box-folder 220: 3-6)
  - "Capitalism and the Jews,", 1971-1984 (Box-folder 220: 7)
  - CBS commentaries, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 220: 8)
  - Committee for Economic Development, "The Most Important Problem to be Faced by the United States in the Next Twenty Years,", 1957 (Box-folder 220: 9)
  - "Do Old Fallacies Ever Die?,", 1992-1993 (Box-folder 221: 1)
  - Dollars and Deficits, 1964-1975 (Box-folder 221: 2)
  - An Economist's Protest, 1972-1984 (Box-folder 221: 3)
  - Free to Choose correspondence, 1978-2006 (bulk 1980-1985)
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
    - Book
      - A-K (Box-folder 221: 4-9)
      - L-Z (Box-folder 222: 1-9)
      - Reviews, 1980 (Box-folder 222: 10)
    - Television series
      - Reviews, 1980 (Box-folder 223: 1)
      - A-F (Box-folder 223: 2-9)
      - G-M (Box-folder 224: 1-7)
      - N-V (Box-folder 225: 1-8)
      - W-Z (Box-folder 226: 1-4)
    - Party, 1997 (Box-folder 226: 5)
  - Friedman in China preface, 1990 (Box-folder 226: 6)
  - Friedman, Milton at the University of Wisconsin, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 226: 7-8)
  - Hoarding correspondence with Moses (Moe) Abramowitz, undated (Box-folder 226: 9)
  - Income from Independent Professional Practice, undated (Box-folder 226: 10)
  - "In Defense of Destabilizing Speculation,", circa 1954 (Box-folder 226: 11)
  - India, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 226: 12)
  - Journal of Money, Credit, and Banking, 1967-1996 (Box-folder 227: 1-2)
  - Journal of Political Economy, 1957-1994 (Box-folder 227: 3)
  - Meet the Press
    - 1970 June 28 (Box-folder 227: 4)
    - 1976 October 24 (Box-folder 227: 5)
    - 1978 November 12 (Box-folder 227: 6)
    - 1982 March 21 (Box-folder 227: 7)
  - Money Mischief, 1991-2000 (Box-folder 227: 8-9)
  - Newsweek columns
    - Editorial correspondence (Box-folder 228: 1-2)
    - General correspondence (Box-folder 228: 3-4)
    - Reader reaction correspondence
      - 1966-1969 (Box-folder 228: 5-16)
      - 1970-1974 June (Box-folder 229: 1-25)
      - 1974 September-1977 (Box-folder 230: 1-23)
      - 1978-1983 (Box-folder 231: 1-18)
  - Playboy interview, 1973 (Box-folder 232: 1)
  - The Power of Choice, 2004 (Box-folder 232: 2)
    Video production based on Two Lucky People.
  - Press, University of Chicago, 1954-2002 (Box-folder 232: 3-4)
  - Radio and television, University of Chicago, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 232: 5)
  - "Reduction of Fluctuations in the Incomes of Primary Producers,", 1953-1954 (Box-folder 232: 6)
  - Quarterly Journal of Economics, 1935-1937 (Box-folder 232: 7)
  - "Savings and the Balance Sheet,", 1954-1957 (Box-folder 232: 8)
  - Schuman Plan, 1950-1953 (Box-folder 232: 9)
  - Science article, 1980 October 3 (Box-folder 232: 10)
  - Statistical Research Group, Columbia University, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 232: 11)
  - Theory of the Consumption Function, 1951-1956 (Box-folder 232: 12-13)
  - There's No Such Thing as a Free Lunch, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 233: 1)
  - Turner column, New York Times, 1977 December (Box-folder 233: 2)
  - Two Lucky People (memoirs), 1991-1998 (Box-folder 233: 3-9)
    Correspondence, notes, and reviews.
  - Tyranny of the Status Quo
    - Book, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 234: 1-2)
    - Television program transcripts, circa 1984 (Box-folder 234: 3-10)
  - "What All Is Utility?,", 1955 (Box-folder 234: 11)
  - Wall Street Journal, 1968-2003 (Box-folder 234: 12-14)
- Incremental Sound Recordings, 1966-1999 (Boxes 234-236)
  Boxes 235-236 CLOSED. Use the provided copy reference numbers to listen to recordings in the Archives reading room. Some recordings also available online at miltonfriedman.hoover.org.
  Sound cassettes of speeches, interviews, and travel.
  - Milton Friedman Speaks, 1977-1978; 35.0 sound cassettes
    Sound recordings of the original lectures upon which the series (consisting of 15 videotaped lectures) is based.
    - Brochure, 1980 (Box-folder 234: 15)
    - "Who Protects the Consumer?," lecture delivered at Pfizer Corporation, New York, 1977 September 12; 2.0 sound cassettes (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0006837
      Summary from brochure: Consumer legislation doesn't in the end protect the consumer; rather, it benefits the consumer advocates, including reformers, special interest groups, and regulatory agencies. What does protect the consumer? Alternative sources of supply at variable prices are the inevitable result of international competition--free trade.
      "Let me emphasize: Competition does not protect the consumer because businessmen are more soft hearted than bureaucrats or because they are more altruistic or because they are more generous, but only because it is in the self-interest of the entrepreneur to protect the consumer."
    - "Putting Learning Back in the Classroom," lecture delivered at a meeting of Harlem Parents for Vouchers, New York City, 1977 September 15; 2.0 sound cassettes (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0006838
      Summary from brochure: The quality of public education in America today in many places is deplorable. Dr. Friedman identifies (1) the increasing centralization and bureaucratization of the educational establishment, which inhibits educators from seeing and responding to the needs of their "consumers"--parents and students; (2) our altered view of the relationship between the individual and society--the shift from seeing the individual as responsible for oneself to seeing the individual as someone controlled by social forces. An obvious solution is to give power back to the parents. The voucher system is an especially effective means of exercising that power; it can foster competition among public and private institutions and incite them to offer us a better quality educational "product."
      "In the nineteenth century, the schools, even in crowded cities and in urban cities, might not have been affluent, they might not have had the best facilities, but they had an atmosphere in which the individual was made responsible for his own development and learning... In the twentieth century, the concept has been that the schools are an expression of society's values and interests which should be imposed upon the child."
    - "Is Capitalism Humane?," lecture delivered at Cornell University, 1977 September 27; 3.0 sound cassettes (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0007222
      Summary from brochure: The question is irrelevant. Capitalism per se is not humane or inhumane. Nor is socialism. If we compare the two in terms of results, it is clear that only capitalism fosters equality and works toward social justice. The one is based on the principle of voluntary cooperation and free exchange, the other on force of position and power. In a free economy, it is hard to do good--you either have to use your own hard-earned money to do it or work hard to persuade others to your course. But by the same token, it is difficult to do harm because by preventing a concentration of power, capitalism prevents people from committing sustained, serious harm. Is capitalism humane or inhumane? It is neither. But it tends to give free rein to the human values of human beings.
      "Capitalism has repelled people, it has driven them away from supporting it, because they have thought it emphasized self-interest in a narrow way. They were repelled by the idea of people pursuing their own interests rather than some broader interests. Yet it is clear that the results go the other way around. Only those countries in which capitalism has prevailed over long periods have experienced both freedom and prosperity."
      Additional summary generated by Hoover: At the beginning, Friedman, clearly animated, responds to protestors criticizing his work in Chile. He also speaks about what freedom of speech means.
    - "Who Protects the Worker?," lecture delivered before a live studio audience at WQLN-TV, Erie, Pennsylvania, 1977 September 29; 2.0 sound cassettes (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0007235
      Unions offer protection to workers in some situations, but union membership represents only one fifth of the American labor force. And while some unions do benefit their members, it is generally at the expense of competing works and frequently at the expense of the consumer. Government? Government provides some protection, but its efforts are minor. Some workers with only one possible employer--or with no possible employer--enjoy very little protection. The right answer to the question "Who protects the worker?" is that the worker is protected by employers--by the existence of other employers who can and will compete for his or her services if a present employer fails to provide decent wages and working conditions. The only real way to protect the standard of living of the American worker is to preserve a freely competitive market.
      "Workers are protected by employers. Not by [their] own employer[s], because the man who has only one possible employer has no protection. The employers who protect the worker are the people who would like to hire him but for whom he doesn't work. The real protection that a worker gets is the existence of more than one possible employer."
    - "What Is America?," lecture delivered at the University of Chicago, 1977 October 3; 2.0 sound cassettes (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0007225
      Summary from brochure: Is America still the land of opportunity, or is it a land worn thin, showing much bureaucracy and less freedom? Dr. Friedman's view of America's present situation is not sanguine. He identifies the chief problem and its corollary solution: We must restore the prestige and influence of the single mechanism most responsible for America's greatness--the free market. Our greatest defense against becoming over-governed is the free market.
      "I believe very deeply that we are nearing the point of no return. We still have the choice, but if we continue much longer along the road that we have been going we no longer shall have the choice. We shall degenerate into a society which will lose that spark of creativity, that spark of independence, of freedom, that we have all loved in our country."
    - "Myths That Conceal Reality," lecture delivered at Utah State University, 1977 October 13; 4.0 sound cassettes (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0007226
      Summary from brochure: Five myths cloud our perception of both the past and the present. (1) The "robber baron" myth which holds that in late nineteenth-century America there were powerful men who became rich at the expense of the poor. The reality is that they became wealthy by being productive, and that there is no other period in history which saw such a rapid and widespread improvement in the well-being of the average individual. (2) The myth that the Great Depression was caused by a failure of business. It was, in fact, produced by the Federal Reserve System. (3) The myth that government in the economy has expanded in response to public demand. Actually, the pubic has had to be sold "hard" for politicians to enact every major social program. (4) The "free lunch" myth. No matter how the government raises money--by taxing individuals, by taxing businesses, or by printing more money--it is the individual who pays. (5) The myth that government, like Robin Hood, transfers wealth from the rich to the poor. The reality is that the government usually transfers wealth and income from both the very rich and the very poor to those in the middle.
      "The Great Depression was produced... by a failure of government, by a failure of monetary policy. It was produced by a failure of the Federal Reserve System to act in accordance with the intentions of those who established it. It was produced by a failure of the Federal Reserve System despite the presence of knowledge on the part of many of the people in the System about the right course of action."
      An unrelated program is also on the third original cassette.
    - "Money and Inflation," lecture delivered under the auspices of the University of San Diego and the San Diego Chamber of Commerce, 1977 November 7; 2.0 sound cassettes (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0007230
      Summary from brochure: Inflation is blamed on many things. But it has only one cause: It is a monetary phenomenon. Inflation occurs when the quantity of money increases faster than the quantity of goods. Why does the money supply increase? Very often, it does so to enable the government to pay its bills without raising taxes. There's only one real cure for inflation. It is a cure that's easy to describe but difficult to apply: The government must reduce spending and print less money. The alternatives are both recession and double-digit inflation.
      "Printing money is a very attractive device because inflation, from the point of view of a person sitting in Congress or in the Senate, is a wonderful tax. He doesn't have to vote for it. Have you ever known a congressman who got up and said, 'I vote to impose a tax in the form of inflation of 10 percent next year'?"
    - "Is Tax Reform Possible?," lecture delivered before a meeting of the Americanism Education League, Pasadena, California, 1978 February 6; 3.0 sound cassettes (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0007223
      Summary from brochure: Why do Americans pay more in taxes than they really want to? Can they do anything about it? Americans must understand that their true tax burden is what the government spends--regardless of who that spending is financed--and that if government spending goes up faster than prices in general, the real tax burden increases. Simplifying the system is far from easy, but the real defect is not in the tax system, anyway, but in the budget structure. Our only hope for tax reduction is in establishing constitutional provisions that will set limits on government spending.
      "In no way is anybody proposing to cut taxes because President Carter has proposed an increase in federal government spending, an increase which is larger than the anticipated increase in prices; so it's an increase in real terms and indeed a larger increase than that which appears in his official budget because of the continued use and invention of more and more sophisticated methods to conceal actual spending, the latest gimmick being to treat subsidies given by the government as refunds of taxes collected from somebody else."
    - "The Role of Government in a Free Society," lecture delivered at Stanford University, 1978 February 9; 2.0 sound cassettes (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0007241
      Summary from brochure: John Stuart Mill said, in effect, that self-protection is the only legitimate reason for people to interfere with the freedom of others. If we are to define the role of government in a free society, we must first specify what we mean by self-protection. Defense from foreign enemies and protection of property, including the enforcement of private contracts, are clearly legitimate functions of government. But when we come to two other functions of government--providing a substitute for voluntary cooperation when it appears impossible to achieve, and providing for irresponsible individuals--the justification is much less clear-cut, because in a free society people should be able to take risks but should not be able to force others to pay the consequences. If the proper limitations of government action were observed, the government would not do many things it now does. We should not resort to government regulation until we have adequately explored the possibilities for coordinating our activities through voluntary means. If we understood the implications of our own values, we would not allow ourselves to be "front men" for values we oppose merely because we are confused about the meaning of freedom and the legitimate role of government in a free society.
      "You and I as well-meaning people may say that government should step in to correct this or that market failure, but once we get the government into the act it's going to go according to its own rules, and those rules will mean that the ultimate results are very different than the initial intent. The will will be different than the deed. When the government steps in and make mistakes and has failures, they're going to be big failures and not little ones."
    - "The Energy Crisis: A Humane Solution," lecture delivered at the Bank of America, San Francisco, California, 1978 February 10; 2.0 sound cassettes (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0007233
      Summary from brochure: It's pointless to try to predict the availability of adequate sources of energy. What we need is an adjustable mechanism to enable us to adapt to whatever happens. We already have such a mechanism: The market helps us make transitions to the future--just as it has done in the past--if it is allowed to operate freely. Our present energy crisis exists because this crucial mechanism has not been allowed to function freely. Our prospects will be much improved if we can devise means to abolish--or at least work around--the government controls that interfere with the production and distribution and use of energy.
      "We tend to forget that the price and wage control measures of 1971 bear a great deal of responsibility for our present oil problem. They have been eliminated on every other product but not on oil. The retention of price controls on oil has discouraged production, encouraged consumption, increased the fraction of our energy that comes from abroad, and established new vested interests in the maintenance of controls."
    - "The Future of Our Free Society," lecture delivered before a meeting of the National Association of Manufacturers/National Industrial Council, Congress of American Industry, Washington, D.C., 1978 February 21; 2.0 sound cassettes (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0007238
      We live under a form of slavery--government domination of the market economy. We have come a long way from a truly free economy: consider the number of markets to which new firms do not have free access; consider the erosion of expression for business people; consider the plethora of government regulations American business must contend with. Can these trends be reversed? It is harder to repeal laws than pass them. Private business is unfortunately short-sighted when it turns to politics. But count among the favorable signs the very inefficiency of government--and the American public's growing recognition of this fact. Business qua business can do relatively little to reverse this trend (though it can at least become more sophisticated and farsighted in political planning), but business people as individuals, as citizens, must seek to persuade the public that we are already on the road to a collectivist state, that if we continue it, we will lose prosperity and liberty.
      "If we continue the trend to a collectivist economy, continue the trend to a society controlled by government, we shall lose not only our economic advantages but also our political freedom. We cannot continue half slave and half free, and if we continue in the direction of slavery we shall end up as a collectivist totalitarian society."
    - "What Is Wrong with the Welfare State?," lecture delivered at the University of Rochester, 1978 February 23; 4.0 sound cassettes (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0007239
      Friedman examines how the welfare state, though under "noble objectives," is not sustainable. He focuses not just on the United States since the New Deal, but taking the countries of Europe and New York City's city government into consideration as well.
    - "Free Trade: Producer vs. Consumer," lecture delivered at the Alfred M. Landon Lecture at Kansas State University, 1978 April 27; 2.0 sound cassettes (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0007231
      Summary from brochure: If free trade is good, why is protectionism so popular? Part of the answer lies in a simple political principle--interests that are concentrated (those of the producer) are more politically effective than interests that are diffuse (those of the consumer). Protectionism does not create jobs or move goods; rather, it forces us to expend greater effort to get the goods we produce, since they cost more to produce at home than abroad. The balance of payments can take care of itself, provided we do not manipulate foreign exchange markets to put an artificial value on the dollar. The right solution is to dismantle systematically our own trade barriers and set an example for the rest of the world.
      "The people who are harmed by [trade] protection are spread and diffused. Indeed the very language shows the political pressure. We call a tariff a protective measure. It does protect; it protects the consumer very well against one thing. It protects the consumer against low prices. And yet we call it protection."
    - "Equality and Freedom in the Free Enterprise System," lecture delivered under the sponsorship of NASA at the College of William and Mary, Newport News Campus, 1978 May 1; 2.0 sound cassettes (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0007236
      Summary of brochure: If the government has the power and responsibility to promote equality of income, then how do we define the concept of equality? Jefferson, in his Declaration of Independence, meant equality before the law, a concept necessary precisely because people are not equal in tastes, values, or capacities. Later, equality came to mean equality of opportunity--the chance to run a fair race. Within a free market system, both definitions are consistent with other values: Efficiency, justice, and liberty. More recently, equality has come to mean equality of outcome. Equality of outcome cannot be mandated, cannot be insured. Any serious attempt to achieve it would destroy freedom.
      "Any society that puts equality before freedom will end up with neither. On the other hand, a society that puts freedom first will, as a happy byproduct, end up with both greater freedom and greater equality."
    - "The Economics of Medical Care," lecture delivered at the Mayo Foundation, Rochester, Minnesota, 1978 May 19; 1.0 sound cassette (Box 235)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0007229
      Summary from brochure: Increasing government involvement in medical care will take us toward fully socialized medicine. This trend is clearly against the interests of patients, physicians, and other health care personnel. There is of course no such thing as free health care--you either pay for it directly, or via the tax system, with bureaucrats taking their usual cut along the way. The reality of the situation is that government involvement in the economics of medical care leads directly to higher costs for that care. There is no special role for government in medical care. Government should do there only what it does in other fields--enforce laws against fraud and deception, and offer some assistance (comparable to flood or tornado relief) to those in extreme medical distress.